<?xml version="1.0" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "../common/TEI-transcr-TC.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 	<teiHeader>
 		<fileDesc>
 			<titleStmt>
 				<title>Ad4</title>
					<respStmt n="General">
 						<resp>Textual editing and encoding:</resp>
 						<name>Transcription: Peter Robinson, Barbara Bordalejo and members of the Canterbury Tales Project at Oxford and Sheffield (1992-1998), De Montfort University, Leicester (1998-2005), Birmingham (2005-2010), Saskatoon (2010-2013), Virginia Tech, New York University, University of Murcia, Adam Mickiewicz University (Poznan) and Brigham Young University. </name>
 					</respStmt>
 			</titleStmt>
 				<publicationStmt>
 				<publisher>Textual Communities and the Canterbury Tales Project, University of Saskatchewan</publisher>
 				<pubPlace>Saskatoon</pubPlace>
 				<date>2014</date>
 				<availability>
 					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
 					<p>Creative Commons Attribution Share-Alike Unported.</p>
 					<p>All republication of all or any part of this transcript must credit its creators and all who have contributed to it, as listed in the sourceDesc element, and make available free-to-all any work derived from this resource under the same license.</p>
 					<p>Commercial republication is permitted, in accordance with these terms.</p>
 					</licence>
 				</availability>
 			</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
 			<bibl type="summary">
			<respStmt n="General">
				<resp>Textual editing and encoding:</resp>
				<name>Transcription: Peter Robinson, Barbara Bordalejo and members of the Canterbury Tales Project at Oxford and Sheffield (1992-1998), De Montfort University, Leicester (1998-2005), Birmingham (2005-2010), Saskatoon (2010-2014), Virginia Tech, New York University, University of Murcia, Adam Mickiewicz University (Poznan) and Brigham Young University. </name>
			</respStmt>
 		</bibl>
 		<bibl type="transcribers">
 			<respStmt n="Oxford">
 				<resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
 						<name>Oxford transcription team, 1992-1998: Peter Robinson, Elizabeth Solopova, Lorna Stevenson, with contributions from James McCabe, Hubert Stadler, Cathy Swires, Paul and Maureen Watry, Laura Wright,  Diana Wyatt and Simon Horobin</name>
 					</respStmt>
 			<respStmt n="Sheffield-C">
  				<resp >Corrections:</resp>
 						<name>Sheffield transcription team, 1992-1998, led by Norman Blake: Michael Pidd and Estelle Stubbs, with Linda Cross, Claire Thomson and Simon Horobin</name>
 					</respStmt>
			<respStmt n="DMU">
 				 <resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
 				<name>De Montfort transcription team, 1998-2005: Peter Robinson, Barbara Bordalejo, Orietta Da Rold, Gavin Cole, Pip Willcox, Jennifer Marshall, Takako Kato, Jacob Thaisen, Nicole Green</name>
 					</respStmt>
			<respStmt n="UoS">
 				 <resp>Conversion for Textual Communities:</resp>
 				<name>University of Saskatchewan  team, 2010-2013: Peter Robinson and Barbara Bordalejo</name>
 					</respStmt>
		<respStmt n="VT">
 				 <resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
 				<name>Virgina Tech team, led by Daniel W. Mosser</name>
 		</respStmt>
		<respStmt n="NYU">
 				 <resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
 				<name>New York University team, led by David Hoover and Martha Rust, 2003-2006.</name>
 		</respStmt>
 		<respStmt n="BYU">
 				 <resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
 				<name>Brigham Young University transcription team, 1995-2006, led by Paul Thomas: Sara Black, Jessica Cox, Barbara Christiansen, Kerry Clift Spencer*, Heidi Elldredge, Leona Fisher Sankhla, Kela Flint*, Melissa Gallup, Shannon Harris, Rebecca Johnson, Mary Jorgensen, Darin Merrill*, Wesley Pack*, Jared Perkins, Jon Penny, Randall Rogers, Ryan Rowberry*, Sara Slack, Carie Soderquist Jackson*, Kat Southerland, Matt Tenney, Briton Wright, John Young. Asterisks after names denote those who supervised the other transcribers.</name>
 		</respStmt>
 		 <respStmt n="Poznan">
 				<resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
 						<name>Adam Mickiewicz University, Poznan, transcription team, 2007-2010: (names to be supplied), with support from Adam Mickiewicz University and the The Polish Ministry for Science and Higher Education, grant N104 045 32/4256.</name>
 					</respStmt>
 		 		 <respStmt n="Murcia">
 				<resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
 						<name>Nila Vazquez Gonzalez, University of Murcia. </name>
 					</respStmt>
			<respStmt n="Sheffield-C">
  				<resp >Corrections:</resp>
 						<name>Sheffield transcription team, 1994-1999, led by Norman Blake: Michael Pidd and Estelle Stubbs, with Linda Cross, Claire Thomson and Simon Horobin</name>
 					</respStmt>
  		</bibl>
  		<bibl type="notcontributed">
  			<respStmt n="MU">
  				<resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
  				<name>University of Münster, Germany, c. 2000-2004,led by Gabriele Müller Oberhauser; transcribed by Ulrike Grassnick. The manuscripts of the Pardoner's Tales were transcribed in partnership with the Canterbury Tales Project, using images and other resources supplied by the Project. No part of these transcripts is contained in this iteration of the Project.</name>
  			</respStmt>
  			<respStmt n="Sheffield">
  				<resp>Original capture and corrections:</resp>
  				<name>University of Sheffield, 1994-1999, led by Norman Blake: Michael Pidd and Estelle Stubbs, with Linda Cross, Claire Thomson, Orietta Da Rold and Simon Horobin. In partnership with the Canterbury Tales Project, at that time led by Norman Blake in partnership with Peter Robinson and Elizabeth Solopova (up to 1998), and using images and other resources supplied by the Project, the Sheffield team transcribed eight manuscripts in full (Ad3, Corpus, Dd, Gg, Ellesmere, Ha4, Hengwrt, Lansdowne), sections of some seven other manuscripts, and all manuscripts of the Franklin's Tale.  No part of these transcripts is contained in this iteration of the Project.</name>
  			</respStmt>
	</bibl>

 	<bibl type="transcripts">
				<respStmt n="GP">
						<resp>Original transcription and corrections:</resp>
 						<name n="Oxford Sheffield-C  ESolopova UoS">Original: and corrections Oxford transcription team and published in Elizabeth Solopova's edition; corrections: Sheffield team; conversion for Textual Communities: Saskatchewan team.</name>
 					</respStmt>
		</bibl>
			 <msDesc>
 				  	<msIdentifier>
 				  	 <settlement>London</settlement>
  					<repository>British Library</repository>
  					<idno>Additional MS 10340</idno>
  					<msName>Ad4</msName>
  					</msIdentifier>
 			 </msDesc>
 	
</sourceDesc>
 		</fileDesc>
 		<encodingDesc>
   			<refsDecl>
   				<p>Optimized for Textual Communities input.</p>
 	 		</refsDecl>
 		</encodingDesc>
 	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
<pb n="41r" facs="Ad4-41r.jpg"/>
<div  n="GP" type="G">
<lb/><l n="480">Þere was a pore <am>ꝑ</am><ex>per</ex>son of a toune </l>
<lb/><l n="479">And was a goode man of religioune </l>
<lb/><l n="481">Holy he was boþe in þouȝt ⁊ werk </l>
<lb/><l n="482">Þerto he was alered man a clerk </l>
<lb/><l n="493">Were hys <am>ꝑ</am><ex>per</ex>isshe housed neuer so fer a sonder </l>
<lb/><l n="494">He lefte neiþer for reynes ne for þonder </l>
<lb/><l n="495-a">Þe ferrest in hys <am>ꝑ</am><ex>per</ex>ische to visite </l>
<lb/><l n="492">He couþe haue suffisau<am>̄</am><ex>n</ex>ce in þing ful lite </l>
<lb/><l n="488">Ful loþe was hym to cursen for his tyþes </l>
<lb/><l n="487">And so he was p yproued ofte syþes </l>
<lb/><l n="497">Þus wolde he walke ⁊ in hys hand a staf  </l>
<lb/><l n="498">Þis noble ensample in to hys shepe he ȝaf </l>
<lb/><l n="499">Þat fyrst he wrouȝt ⁊ afterward he tauȝt </l>
<lb/><l n="500">Out of þe gospel he þo wordes rauȝt </l>
<lb/><l n="509">He lete nauȝt hys benefice to hyr </l>
<lb/><l n="510">And lete hys shepe emco<am>̄</am><ex>m</ex>bred in þe myr </l>
<lb/><l n="511">Ne ran to londou Vnto seynt poules </l>
<lb/><l n="512">To getyn hym a chauntery for soules </l>
<lb/><l n="513">Oþer wiþ abreþerhede to be . wiþholde      </l>
<lb/><l n="514">But knelt at home ⁊ he kept hys owe<am>̄</am><ex>m</ex> fold </l>
<lb/><l n="515">So þat þe wolf ne made it nat myskary </l>
<lb/><l n="516">He was a shepherde ⁊ nat amercenary </l>
<lb/><l n="501">And þis figure he added eke þerto </l>
<lb/><l n="502">Þat if gold rust what shal yren do </l>
<lb/><l n="503">For ȝif a prest be foule on whom we trust </l>
<lb/><l n="504">No wonder is a lewed man to rust </l>
<lb/><l n="505-a">For it is a foule þing who so take kepe </l>
<lb/><l n="506">A sheten shepherd ⁊ a clene shepe </l>
<lb/><l n="527">He wayted aftr no pompe ne reu<am>ꝰ</am><ex>er</ex>ence </l>
<lb/><l n="528">Ne made hym a spiced conscience </l>
<lb/><l n="529">But cristis lore ⁊ hys apostles tweue </l>
<lb/><l n="530">He tauȝt but first he folwed it hym selue . </l>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>

